I had been in the army for three years,
until I got kicked out...
because there were some corpses
that had to be buried.
My lieutenant gave me
the order to bury them.
But I didn’t. Instead I sold them
to some people who approached me.
They wanted me to sell them.
That they would use them for a play...
or something like that.
They told me not to worry,
that nobody would find out.
So I believed them and
I sold them the corpses.
I found out later what they
were really going to do with them.
They would disguise them
and leave them in the mountains as
if they would have died in combat.
I kept silence until they were
declared as "false positives".
MUTE FIRE
On February 10th 1906, four men
tried to murder the president of Colombia.
The staging of that event, was the
beginning of cinema in the country.
The newspaper "Correo Nacional",
published in Bogotá on March 6th, 1906,
the exact and vivid account
of the execution of four men
for the attempt of murder of
the General Rafael Reyes,
by that time president
of Colombia.
Marco Arturo Salgar, Carlos Roberto Gonzalez,
Juan Ortiz and Fernando Aguilar.
were the four men sentenced
to death, and in consequence
shot in the same place where
they committed the crime.
The account, whose author's
name remains unknown,
is extremely detailed.
For example, he describes one by one the kind
of hat that each condemned was wearing.
It’s worth quoting the whole fragment:
"They were all wearing black:
Salgar wore a straight wing cinnamon hat.
Aguilar wore a Panama hat.
Gonzales, a black Tyrolean hat.
And Ortiz wore a black hard hat."
The reporter also collects
a series of interviews.
The most striking is perhaps, the one from
the Captain of Executions, who just says,
in a serious tone I'd guess:
"Nothing is sacred".
The reporter states: "The shooting
proceeds as normal.
Given the signal with his sword
by the Captain of Executions,
the first round of shooting
resounds from the rifles.
Afterwards, a group of doctors approaches
and certify that the condemned
are still breathing,
and give the order for
a second shooting,
which ends with the immediate
entrance of the four coffins
to transport the corpses
to the cemetery."
This time, the event is more relevant than
usually, since president Rafael Reyes
guided by this moment of political
instability, makes an exception
and the shooting doesn't take place in
the courtyard of the School of Infantry,
where it would normally happened.
Instead, it's held in a public area,
in front of over 10,000 people.
Rafael Reyes saw here the
remains of the last civil war
that had ended only four years ago,
and still had the country in agony.
Shooting people of his same
political party in public areas,
was for him a sign of authority,
but also an invitation to end
the traditional divide
between the liberal
and the conservative party.
With the purpose of making this shooting
visible to as many people as possible
Reyes publishes the book "February 10th",
telling the events through photos.
Reyes thought that, just like the people
who witnessed the shooting in person did,
everyone who saw those photos
would immediately support his idea.
Nevertheless, the most interesting
part of this series of photos
happens after the moment
of the cemetery picture.
It’s unknown whose idea it was, but due to the
impact caused by the pictures of the execution
president Rafael Reyes, Chief of police
Pedro Pedraza, and photographer Lino Lara
decided together to recreate
the moments before the shooting.
They decided to recreate
the attack on the president
and the capture of the condemned,
to create a story.
The outcome was what the historians
called a "false document".
From the 22 pictures that make up
the story, 18 are theatrical reenactments.
This is the first time of a tale made
through photographs in Colombia.
This little narrative gesture,
is acknowledged by tradition
as the beginning of
filmmaking in the country.
Here lays the body of Rafael Reyes today.
This was going to be a movie about the
beginnings of Cinema in Colombia,
about its first images.
But as it's being said:
To talk about Colombia
we have to talk about war.
And to talk about war we need to talk about
armies, about deaths, about cemeteries.
At the same time, my house and my
parents house looked like a cemetery.
It felt like haunted by an inert current,
like flooded by murky water
or better, by dead water.
A few months ago my mother
had an episode of mutism,
and without any explanation,
she just stopped talking.
I remember with some nostalgia
how she repeated the words of that
Mexican musician while cooking:
that said something like:
"I wish you to be happy, very happy...
I wish you to find love,
because you deserve it"
I read somewhere that the first thing you
forget about a person is the voice.
Affected by this
familiar incident,
and because of what connects
all things together
maybe the first moments
of national cinema
and the muteness of my mother can
be part of the same scenario.
Like when you look at a surface
where shadows are being projected
and you can't tell each
object from the other apart.
One night my father woke up and saw
the light of the bathroom on.
When he came closer, he saw my mother in
front of the mirror, shaking.
My father hugged her and
asked her what was going on,
he asked her if she
had a bad dream
but she couldn’t answer.
Since that moment,
she has never spoken again.
My mother spent most of the time locked in a
room looking at people through the window.
Her presence had become more and
more unbearable for my father
who couldn’t avoid feeling sometimes
guilty, and sometimes cheated.
The ambiguity of the doctors answers
left a bad feeling behind
which made him think
that she was just pretending.
One day, a worker of the family suggested
to try with another type of specialist
from his point of view, my mother's
muteness was due to a powerful spell.
My father agreed, even if it
would make him feel humiliated
because for him, superstitions
were for fools.
After two weeks some kind of chaman
or warlock came to my mother.
After wandering around the house, where some
kind of weird mantle could certainly be felt
like a thick, rancid
smell, he told my father:
"Your problems have a
solution, don’t worry.
You just have to
sell this house,
and leave somewhere visible a valuable
object and a picture of her."
My father did so.
The house was put on sale, and on a
shelf he left a picture of her
and a black stone that she
held like a luck charm.
Please, put your legs up.
There’s a line dividing the brain
into a left and a right hemisphere.
Usually, in most people,
the left hemisphere
dominates language.
Language works in two important parts.
One part is in the temporal lobe.
The one responsible for perception
and comprehension of any language.
And the other one in the frontal lobe
that’s directly responsible
for performing words.
So that words can coordinate a coherent
answer according to the understood question.
A coherent and adequate answer.
In your case, we’re hoping that you
understand the things we’re asking you.
And in case you would
have any difficulties,
we would find some structural injury
in this part that could be either a tumor
or a scar of some cerebral stroke
that you might have had.
No injury, no tumor.
Analyzing the neurological exam
and this last generation
exam, we can conclude
that Aracellys brain is completely normal.
- Ok. What's your name?
- Gustavo Rojas.
Gustavo Rojas.
No, no. I think it's better alone.
Or I introduce him.
Gustavo Rojas.
Gustavo Rojas, he is chief
of the Kawiyarí tribe...
Well, there's many different ones.
Like Tucanos, and some others...
Let's stop for a minute. One question.
She will ask so you can answer that...
There’s an announcement on
the internet that says:
"Recover all important moments of
your life that are kept in old tapes.
Live those unique moments with
your family and friends again.
All formats, Betacam SP,
VHS, DV, mini DV, 8mm…"
I contacted the advertiser.
That same afternoon, in a country
house on the outskirts of the city,
I got to meet Carlos Pelbet,
founder of an old audiovisual company
that he and his brother had
since the beginning of the 80s.
Carlos told me rapidly about
his interest in films
or rather, he told me that at some
point of his life it was of his interest.
Also that Pelbet, his company,
inaugurated the recording and broadcasting
business of soccer matches in Colombia
and that it was right then, when competing with
the big TV channels, that the company broke.
He told me that a few years ago he started
collecting anonymous family home movies
from the cassettes that he digitizes.
Hours and hours of family events
weddings, first communions, birthdays,
baptisms, Christmas and holidays.
In a sense, my film is
a relative of all these images,
of the personal images of everyday rites.
Carlos tells me that each week, a
different youngster arrives at his door
wanting to digitize
images of his family
with an idea similar to mine:
To make a film about their mothers,
fathers or grandparents.
Apparently more people are doing the
same film as me at this moment.
We are all thinking about the same images.
These are some images taken by my mother.
A movie about a play in
a rural school she worked at.
Back then, she sympathized with the
insurgent groups of the country.
That’s me.
In one of the movie cans,
it was written on a white tape:
"Marquetalia, 1964".
Those are the place and the date
where the famous FARC was founded.
Apparently, the play is about a popular
narration about the first combats
between the FARC guerilla
and the National Army.
The story is the following:
Having the intention of avoiding the
expansion of the communist guerrilla,
on May 18th, 1964 president
Guillermo León Valencia
sends over a thousand soldiers
to the Tolima plateau
in search for a suspected FARC camp with
48 members of the insurgent movement in it.
After nine days of intense
wandering, the group of soldiers,
lead by Lieutenant Colonel
José Joaquín Matallana,
starts suspecting that they’re wrong,
that there’s no such camp.
They quickly realize that the insurgents
are not full time soldiers,
and that most of them actually
have a disguised life as farmers
among the civilians.
A question immediately arose:
How to tell the population, most of them
farmers, from the guerrillas apart?
Facing this, Colonel
José Joaquín Matallana,
who considered himself as an
analytic and methodic person
and an innovating strategist,
thought to have the answer.
He explains to his soldiers: "This problem
is essentially about appearances".
Matallana ordered his soldiers to go
after every man and woman of the area
and force them to wear the
guerrilla uniform in front of them.
Matallana assured his soldiers,
that the uniform had the
strength and essential capacity
to reveal someone's identity.
According to his logic,
wearing the uniform
would immediately reveal if the person
was a real guerilla soldier or not.
After two weeks they had captured 52 people,
including five children and eight elderly.
This idea would be known later
as the Matallana logic.
And what could have been a
brilliant military operation,
ended up being one of the biggest
political failures in history
because, in less than two years, those 48
soldiers would later turn into five thousand.
From then on, the idea of the disguised
guerrilla would become an obsession
in the development of
public opinion in the country.
Throughout the years, the question
would be incessantly repeated:
Who’s really from the guerilla,
and who’s not?
More than 20 years ago
my mother filmed me.
Today, I’m filming her.
Seeing myself in that play,
playing role of a farmer
captured by the army and forced
to dress like a guerilla man
I couldn’t avoid thinking of the
recent events of the war in Colombia.
Thousands of innocent young people were
captured by the National Army of Colombia
and taken to different parts
of the country to be murdered later.
Then, their bodies were
dressed up like guerilla-soldier
and presented in front of the
media like military successes.
It was a systematic
falsification of war events.
Stagings, using real victims
to create a story.
By the year 2008, this practice
was so common in the National Army
that the victims of this type of
crime counted to the present day
are more than the missing people
during the dictatorship in Chile.
During the 1960s,
in search of images of
true revolutionaries,
two French filmmakers
travelled to Riochiquito,
located in the north of
the province of Cauca.
They recorded there the activities
of the recently founded FARC.
In 1964, the government
started a persecution again.
This time, with 16,000 men ordered to wipe
out completely with the organization.
But again, they encountered with
the resistance of the farmers
and instead of ending it, the movement
has spread and got even stronger.
Since in June 1964 we had already...
created a program that was already
well known by the public opinion.
Many other revolutionary
movements have also joined in.
They also agree with it and
will fight together with us.
According to a French article called
"Cinema declares war on us"
the screening of this movie
generated an unexpected anguish
among young people in Paris.
Apparently, proving the
existence of revolutionary life
radically buried any other
alternative of life.
For the young Parisians of that time
nothing could be compared to the idea
of leading a life in the armed struggle
for political transformation.
Hence,
the movie made them feel
that their lives and
experiences were insignificant
compared to those of Colombian guerilla.
Louise Canet, a western
movies director,
then recently joined to
the French Socialist Party
declared after watching the movie:
"It’s common to hear people saying that
South American people are violent by nature
that they have a violent heritage from
the Spanish and the Indigenous people.
I don’t know what to think.
But I’m sure of something:
It’s a fertile land for rebels".
This is the place where the attempt against
president Rafael Reyes happened
and where the four men who
did it were shot later on.
In the same place, just a few
weeks later, photographer Lino Lara
and Commandant Pedro Pedraza
recreated the attempt of murder.
According to the records
of the Correo Nacional,
the pictures were
taken in two days
and only during morning hours.
From those two days, a brief
correspondence between Lino Lara
and General Pedro Pedraza
hast been preserved.
Here, after making it clear
that he’s also a photographer
and not a superstitious person,
officer Pedraza asks himself:
is there any risk in imitating the dead?
There is no known answer from
Lino Lara to this question.
In fact, very little
is known about him.
In contrast, a lot has been
written about these photographs
and the importance of violent
events reenactments in the country.
It's easy to think that the idea of
this first tale has been influenced
by some of the first films
of Thomas Alva Edison
in which episodes of famous
executions are recreated.
For example: Here they recreate
the death of Leon Czolgosz
a Polish anarchist sentenced to death for the
murder of the president of the United States,
William McKinley, on
September the 6th, 1901.
Edison's goal was to
publicize the electric chair
to make it the new method of execution in
the country and replace the gallows.
He knew that neither technology, nor
his inventions were neutral
and since electricity could be
turned into a killing device
the cinematograph and the pictures
could also unleash very useful energies
for the project of a country.
These landscapes of the Magdalena river
were recorded in photographs
by Rafael Reyes in 1909.
Back then, the former president dedicated himself
to travel around the unknown national territory
thinking about how Colombian cinema could be
used according to the project of a country.
The result of this 22-day-long
adventure was a book called:
"Presidential excursions,
notes from a travel journal."
The book contains a detailed inventory of
the main natural resources of the country
in relation to the industrial means
necessary for its exploitation.
For instance:
there's a list of the total length of
the railway tracks of each province
in relation to the increase of hectares
cultivated year by year since 1895.
Reyes intended to boost
several trades,
especially in the areas
of banana plantations.
Therefore, articles from
French and English magazines
recommending the consumption
of bananas were included
arguing that bananas were the most
hygienic and nutritious fruit of them all.
At the same time, this documentation is
accompanied by a series of photographs
that privilege images of landscapes,
agricultural colonies, train tracks
prominent personalities of the
industrial world and workers.
This book was the first visual
record of the national territory.
Rafael Reyes described it as
an "explained cinematograph".
Banana field blueprint
The truth was, Rafael Reyes did not only
intend to create a catalog of wealths
to allure foreign multinationals.
His true purpose was to create a
unified image of the country,
which due to the characteristics
of its geography
suffered from a great lack of
communication among its regions
which by the time was already producing great
losses in large portions of the territory.
Rafael Reyes was looking for something a
little more elusive and much more dangerous.
He was sure that all people of the
country should be united by something,
a supposed "national essence" that
would prevent their dismemberment.
He asked himself: What are we?
The result of a discrete genocide?
Or are we the occasional guardians
of infinite clusters of gold
and immense expanses of water
that turn into fruits?
Driven by the scientific spirit of the time
Reyes saw in the photographic device
the best tool to look for that essence.
He thought: If photographs can capture,
better than anything else in the world
the outstanding feature of the identity of
a subject that is, of course, his face
why wouldn’t it be able,
with enough effort,
to reveal the image of the true face
of these lands and thus, its identity?
A group of the right images
can unify the country.
Thus, Rafael Reyes begins like this
with his obsession with portraits
which would result in the most significant
image of the book and possibly of the time:
The portrait of cacique
José Dolores and his wife
holding a portrait of former
President Rafael Reyes.
It has been thought, quite often,
that Reyes was saying only one
thing with this photograph:
I am Colombia.
The photographs of Rafael Reyes
and Lino Lara
represented a technological
innovation for the country.
From this moment on,
the way in which the different events were
narrated would be radically transformed.
They marked the beginning of an informative
treatment based on the display of images.
For those who, like myself, have experienced the
war in Colombia exclusively through images
those of television,
magazines and newspapers;
the figure of Rafael Rayes
asks us a question:
Is there any link between the production of
images and the war events in the country?
Over the years, the question about who’s
a guerilla combatant and who’s not,
suffers a transformation.
It mutates, becoming the obsession
for one specific image:
The image of the dead guerilla.
The image of the insurgent murdered
at hands of agents of the State
is spread through all
screens of the country.
In a short time, it manages to dominate
the imagination of public opinion
and its production is furiously
demanded from everywhere.
"¡More images!", says the
redactor to the journalist,
the editor to the photographer,
and the General to the soldier.
"I want to see a dead guerrilla
every day", says the president.
But it’s also to be
heard in schools
bars, stores, churches, houses;
among friends and family.
Then, the horror came.
It was discovered that many of those bodies,
and in consequence many of those images
didn’t belong to authentic guerilla-soldier.
That the bodies were
of young innocents disguised,
that everything was a staging
and that the testimonies of the soldiers
were also reproductions of other combats.
The response of the audience
to that truth was apathy.
We all said: Those are the mothers of
the youngsters called "false positives".
Nobody said: "I’m the one who was found dead
in a distant area disguised as a guerilla".
Nobody said: I’m the one
that’s missing.
We just said:
Those have to be the family members of
the murdered people that are protesting
just asking to recover the good
name of their beloved ones.
Nobody said:
I’m one of the "false positives", one of
the State murders that were celebrated.
Real deaths put in combat scenarios
as if the war events in the country would
have been replaced by some kind of parody
by an evil imitation created by war itself.
As if after all these years, the war would
be trying to create its own representations
its own copies.
In 1906, Rafael Reyes
created a "false document"
to produce a story
about an execution.
A century later,
the Colombian Army created the "false positives"
to simulate the victory of the war.
Thus, the "false positives" seem to be
part of a national fiction tradition
that begins with the photographs
of Lino Lara,
with the first staging of violent events
and the birth of Colombian Cinema.
My mother had a recurrent dream that,
according to her, chased her.
In the dream, a coffin was driven
around the streets of the city.
Every time she told it, she said:
"I think of that image as if I was
the dead person inside of the coffin."
"I imagine the people on the streets watching
and thinking in silence: someone died."
I asked her if she ever had
that dream again. She told me yes.
But that it didn’t
matter to her anymore.
Over time, that image had become
boring to her, kind of obvious, pathetic.
Nevertheless,
she had lately started to feel curious about
the identity of the man who drove the car.
She told me: "I’ve been wondering
lately how his hands would be, his lips,
the shape of his teeth.
I want to know his name".
Are you having fun?
More, more, more!
- Are you all right?
- Yes!
Come then, so you can
get some water on you.
My mother has spent the last few months
between hospitals and this house.
The house of Maria, her best friend.
After several months,
the doctors stated that if she didn’t
talk was because she didn’t want to.
Because they couldn’t find
any reason for it.
Other doctors, the most pessimistic
and less reserved ones,
made us understand that she just
didn’t want to live anymore.
The truth is,
the more time passes,
the feeling that my mother
is disappearing grows.
Somehow, every day her presence
resembles more of a ghost.
It’s as if she would have escaped time,
and would be merely a thought of mine.
Today is her birthday.
We thank the Lord because...
He has given us...
an exact and clear message...
and we have understood that message.
It's not that we have a screw loose.
It’s not that we’re crazy,
or that we’re less than you.
It's not that.
It’s just that we accepted
to walk with Jesus Christ.
That’s the difference between you and us.
That’s why, even with fear
we’re here in front of the presence of God
and maybe you, my friend, will say:
The evangelics again...
Making noise again...
Those people who come here just to sing...
who just…
During the last week, an evangelist called
Ricardo Javier has been harassing my mother.
He stands in front of the house to talk to
her about the power of the word of Jesus.
He was saying yesterday:
"Gods kingdom is like a thief.
If we would know when a thief is coming,
nobody would ever be robbed.
Gods kingdom comes when we’re not
expecting it, so keep your eyes open."
♪ I remember when I saw
you for the first time
♪ and my eyes teared up when I looked at you.
♪ I can't deny it, I was
scared to confess to you
♪ how I would adore you.
♪ You looked at me, and I stared at you.
♪ Until one day, we finally
understood each other.
♪ Who could imagine that then
our children would come
♪ To bring joy to this
place for all eternity.
The strange thing was that I didn’t
notice her as worried as I was.
If I wake up mute I would
probably go crazy.
I noticed it was an attitude
that she was assuming.
I could never knew if was just
in front of me or everyone
or facing life.
Maybe she was punishing us all.
But then she stopped speaking.
I don’t think she can’t speak,
I think that she has decided not to speak.
And I think it’s a voluntary decision.
I thought, however, that it
could be a medical issue.
We took her to the doctor
I talked to Héctor, to César
and to other people.
To everyone I thought could know.
They all came to the
same conclusion:
Aracelly's problem
is inexplicable.
It’s not physiological, and it
doesn’t seem psychological either.
Always, always, always, I think
that she always understands us.
She hasn't lost the
capacity of understanding
nor has she lost any
other kind of routines.
She reads, she walks, she thinks,
she insinuates, she takes initiatives.
I think that she is taking somehow revenge.
And I think that, somehow, what she’s pretending
is to make life unbearable to everyone.
If that’s the case, she
should have said it,
and it would have been better
that we would just
have ended everything.
I think that families begin
and families dissolve, families
should not self-destruct.
I think we never talked enough about love.
Because if we had talked
enough about love
we would have understood
it from the beginning.
Love is born, it grows and it
dies like everything in nature.
I believe that the academic attitude is not
only repeating texts in the universities
but to live academically,
and that we have lacked.
This is the first recorded
game of the Atlético Nacional,
in this filmic document
of the Pelbet company.
We will present indistinctly,
according to journalistic consideration
the main games, the ones
we consider essential
for the conquer of the title of 1981.
The team wins 3-0 in his opening game.
The second game in
Armenia was tied 0-0.
The final game of the championship tied
1-1 against Medellín in the first round
and in the second round
they lost against Quindío 0-2.
The first goal was scored by
Victor Luna and Guillermo La Rosa
from the midfield, inside the area
so that he can be, as
usually, close to the goal.
Let’s go for the second victory Verdolaga!
Attention, La Rosa has the ball,
Herrera enters the area.
He kicks gently, but what a
great location of the ball!
These images belong to the thirty-fourth
Colombian professional football tournament
having the Atlético
Nacional team as champion,
after a victory against
América de Cali
with a difference of one goal to zero.
During the tournament, Atlético Nacional
would play a total of 61 matches.
They would win 28, draw 17 and lose 16.
The particularity of this
tournament is due to Carlos Pelbet
and his small family
company, Pelbet S.A.
Along with his brother, four
cameramen and a commentator
Carlos Pelbet recorded all the matches
of Atlético Nacional during the tournament.
This was the first time
that professional cameras were taken
to the football stadiums in the country
and those were also the first efforts to
broadcast the football events in Colombia.
The transmissions made by Carlos
Pelbet were very limited,
since they were designed to
reach a few radio studios only
where the announcers told the listeners
what were seeing on the screens.
Carlos Pelbet says to himself:
I transformed the history of this country
through football and cameras.
I brought the replay and the slow motion.
I educated the eye of many young people.
Carlos stops in this image.
Apparently, the foul can't
be seen clear enough.
But let’s have a look
from the reverse angle.
The one from the cameras at the other side
of the goal, placed by Pelbet’s company.
41 minutes of the
additional stage.
Four minutes left for
Nacional to be the champion.
Look at that karate blow from Gonzalez
Aquino to the peruvian Cesar Cueto.
Just a few minutes left
of the championship final.
After this fall
the referee interprets a
penalty kick and sanctions it.
Immediately, the coach of the
America enters the field
and tells all his players
to leave the game,
arguing lack of guarantees
from the referee.
The game was never finished.
After this event, Carlos Pelbet was harassed
for several days by hundreds of fanatics
who wanted to obtain the
recordings of the game,
with the intention of studying the
images very carefully themselves
together with friends and family.
Repeat them again and
again, frame per frame,
and dissecting that instant
as many times as necessary
until it spoke for itself and said
if the fault was simulated or real.
It's impossible for Carlos Pelbet
to determine that kind of issue.
For him, there is simply no
difference between someone who falls
and someone who
pretends to fall.
More than 30 years after
those first recordings
Carlos keeps working with images
coming from football events.
- Was my exit okay?
- It was fine.
Cut.
Roll camera, roll sound.
- Do I have to clap again?
- Yes, please.
- Ready?
- Yes.
When I started this movie, I was trying to
find out if my mother was pretending or not.
If she had really turned mute,
if she was really dying.
Neither my father nor other relatives
or close friends believed her
nor the doctors nor even
the religious people.
But, in a similar way to
what many experienced
when analyzing the images of the national
Football championship final game
there may be no difference
between someone who suffers
and someone who
pretends to suffer.
So, Carlos points out that
it's useless to judge an image
wanting to discern what's
real in it and what’s not.
For him, images are jus not a good
place to look for the truth.
Then, from the projects of
Thomas Alva Edison, Rafael Reyes
and the recent images that
dramatize deaths and violent events
perhaps it would be
better to ask ourselves:
What effects do these
images have on the living?
Do they have any participation
in the events they represent?
For example these women.
All three are actresses
who pose as if they had lost
a family member in the war
and were claiming for them.
…or something like that.
They told me not to worry,
that nobody would find out.
So I believed them and
sold them the corpses.
I found out later what they
were going to do with them.
That they would disguise them...
…and leave them on the mountains
as if they would have died in combat.
I kept silence until they were
declared as "false positives".
In a similar way to what happened with
the photographs of February 10th
what would be properly considered as
the first film made in Colombia
was also born from the intention to represent
the attempt and death of a political leader.
On October 15th, 1914, a few
blocks from the Capitol
the popular military
hero Rafael Uribe Uribe
received a mortal blow with an ax
on the right side of his head.
The politician was immediately transferred
to a house in the center of the city
where he agonized for
14 hours and finally died.
It’s told that hundreds of his followers
walked all the way back to the Capitol
and with a white handkerchief
in their hands
tried to pick up of the ground
the blood of the politician.
That same afternoon, while
Rafael Uribe Uribe still lived
a few meters from the house where he was,
the Italian brothers Di Doménico
who later would be recognized as
"the fathers of Colombian Cinema"
began with urgency the filming of the
first film of the country, entitled:
"The drama of October 15th",
in which this murder was recreated.
Only one shot from the
film is preserved.
These images are from the same
date but made with other cameras.
However, due to the great
controversy caused by the film
extensive descriptions of their images
can be found in newspapers of the time.
For example, we know that the
film started with a fade
that slowly showed a
portrait of the soldier.
After almost a minute in which the
image was still on the screen
followed a scene that recreated the last
moments of agony and death of the politician.
We also know that the film
could never be fully projected.
Despite the good intentions
of the Di Doménico brothers,
the audience couldn't bear to see
the images of the hero dying
nor could they bare seeing his assassins.
The public opinion
reacted radically
and pursued with the censorship
and destruction of the film.
In their defense, the Italians,
who due to the public harassment
could never make a film again
argued in their favor referring to the
images of Christ dying on the cross.
If the highest institutions such as museums
and churches in all regions of the planet
allocate entire pavilions with the sole function
of protecting the image of Christ dying
it is because Christ reincarnates
in each one of those images.
To adore those images
is to adore the Christ,
those images create the
world of Christianity.
Thus, the Italians thought
that a State is also the
sum of all its images.
For the Di Doménico brothers, destroying
the images of Rafael Uribe Uribe dying
was opting for a country incapable of
imagining and thinking about their dead.
The first film of the Colombian Cinema,
is born, and dies from this event.
This is its only remaining image
the famous image of the woman
holding the patriotic symbols.
I imagine the death
of Rafael Uribe Uribe
with a coffin that crosses the streets,
marking the path of a crowd.
The image of the people that
accompanies their leader.
Perhaps this film by the
Di Doménico brothers
and the events that surrounded it,
allow us to see from a new perspective,
the images made by Rafael Reyes
and Thomas Alva Edison.
A perspective that does not focus
on the truth of the images,
but on the reaction that
the public has before them.
These events highlight that the staging
of death has a relative value.
Rafael Reyes and Thomas Edison
staged the death of rebels.
These images are celebrated
and widely broadcasted.
On the contrary,
the Di Doménico brothers recreated
the death of a beloved political leader
and hurt the sensitivity of the national
public, the images were destroyed.
This shows that the images
collect a sensitivity.
A sensitivity that
only becomes tolerable
when it reflects the image that a
country likes to receive from itself.
These events also reveal
something even simpler:
the survival of certain
images leads to sympathy
and intensifies the idea that there
are deaths worthy of mourning
and others that are not.
When I look at my
mother from a distance,
I feel that at any moment she will say
something and her expression will change.
Maybe all I have to do is wait.
I have decided that I must
believe in her muteness.
I can’t not do it,
when I see her images.
I think that I've been looking
in the wrong places
and the reasons for her muteness
are somewhere else.
Together with Carlos Pelbet, we recreated the
work of a group of forensic anthropologists.
Some years ago in Colombia,
they had started
the search and identification of the bodies
of people missing during the war.
Exhumation units
throughout the national territory
were in search of the deaths who were hidden
underground by the different armies.
Together with some neighbors and friends who
disguised themselves as forensic and military
we walked around some
fields around the village
dug graves and did a
small performance
of the search for the bodies
of those missing persons.
No matter how hard I try
I can't make myself
more than a small idea
of the dimension and cruelty that
the "false positives" meant.
I wonder if, with the purpose
of telling about these crimes
the best way wouldn’t have been through
images invoking the real victims
the bodies of the executed youths, the
testimonies of the relatives, the witnesses
and the people who actually
suffered it in life.
However, I suspect that the same
thing would happened
as it did, when they were first broadcasted
in television across the country.
We would simply close our eyes
to avoid feeling those deaths.
When the "false positives" were presented
as victories of the National Army
they were celebrated and widespread deaths.
But when those same dead people were
stripped of their insurgent disguise
and turned into state crimes
they didn't become a scandalous image.
There was something about the theater they
represented, that the audience clung to.
Perhaps, this is what the
"false positives" warn us from.
That much of the way we feel about
the deaths of the war in the country
is build upon the field of
appearances and images.
The representations that have
been made of the violent events
have directed our sensitivity, making the
war of the country seem tolerable for us
as long as the dead ones remain the same.
The images have become
an instrument of war.
A war is also the history
of its images.
♪ With justice and truth
next to the people it is
♪ with the first fire of the dawn
♪ the little song that was
born in our guerrilla voice
♪ of struggle and future.
♪ With Bolivar, Galán already rode again.
♪ No more weeping and pain of the homeland.
♪ We are people who go after freedom
♪ building the path of peace.
♪ Guerilla of the FARC
with the people to triumph
♪ for the fatherland,
the people and the bread.
♪ Guerilla of the FARC,
with the voice of unity
♪ to achieve freedom.
♪ Guerrilla of the FARC
with the people to triumph
♪ for the fatherland,
the people and the bread.
♪ Guerilla of the FARC,
with the voice of unity
♪ to achieve freedom.
I found a recording made by my mother.
It’s special because she doesn’t appear,
instead her voice is heard.
Near the end she says my name.
It’s August 9, 1996.
Tomorrow is the parade of Silleteros.
Don Carlos Zapata is here with us
who’s going to parade with a
monumental style silleta.
Don Carlos, for how long have you been
participating in the parade?
About ten years now, that I participate
in the parade of Silleteros.
And how many times have you won?
I've only lost twice in ten years.
Because I stopped competing. I've been
the winner for eight years now.
- You stopped competing?
- Yes.
- We wish you good luck for tomorrow.
- Thank you.
Federico.
Federico...
MUTE FIRE